All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is נ"ח.
nun chet. We pick up on נ"ז עמוד ב' nun zayin amud
bet about, oh, 12 lines from the bottom towards the end of
the line, the דף. daf. מקום שנעקר ממנו עבודת כוכבים. Makom shene'ekar
mimenu avodas kochavim. So now we're moving on after all of this
discussion about dreams and some related digressions from the digression. We now
turn back to the משנה mishnah about different ברכות. brachos. And one
ברכה bracha is a place that idolatry has been uprooted from. You
make a ברכה bracha which is עוקר עבודת כוכבים מארצנו oker avodas
kochavim me'artzenu or something like that.
Well, the נוסח הברכה nusach habracha is מארצנו. me'artzenu. So it sounds
like it's specifically ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. שעקר עכו"ם מארצנו. She'akar akum
me'artzenu. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
our Rabbis taught: הרואה מרקוליס, Haro'eh Markulis, if you see Markulis, which
is a particular idol that was worshipped as a type of a
god for the travelers, were little pyramids of stone and stones were
thrown at it, אומר ברוך שנתן ארך אפים לעוברי רצונו. omer Baruch
shenatan erech apayim le'ovrei retzono. So look at this, you make a
ברכה bracha when it is not uprooted, when you see the idol
there, that you say God gives long, you know, extends His anger,
you know, holds back His anger from those that go against His
will. It's an interesting question how you'd categorize it. Not exactly a
ברכת השבח. Birchas Hashevach. Is it a type of a דיין האמת
Dayan Ha'emes like a מידת פורענות? middas puraniyos? I think more it's
a need to give a religious expression to how does one relate
to the phenomenon that there's all of this prevalence of idolatry if
we're supposed to believe, you know, in God and how does God
allow for this? And there's a need to give some religious articulation
to that. So we do it through this ברכה bracha that God
extends His wrath, you know, holds back His wrath even against people
that violate His will.
Presumably with שם ומלכות. shem u'malchus.
All of this ברוך דיין האמת Baruch Dayan Ha'emes is not
ברכת השבח?
Birchas Hashevach? Well, it's—it's powerful. I know. It's an interesting question what
you'd categorize it as. It's sort of like כשם שמברכין על הטוב
כך מברכין על הרע. keshem shemevarchin al hatov kach mevarchin al hara.
So I guess you could call it a ברכת השבח. Birchas Hashevach.
It's so powerful. Right, right. But anyway, I just think this is
a little different. It's not just that we're looking at this as
פורענות, puraniyos, it's that this presents a—I see this as presenting a
theological challenge which is responded to by this ברכה. bracha. You could
say evil also presents, you know, פורענות puraniyos also presents a theological
challenge. Anyway, here the particular ברכה bracha and yes, presumably according to
the ראשונים Rishonim that say the ברכות brachos here are שם ומלכות,
shem u'malchus, it includes this. Now, מקום שנעקר ממנו עבודת כוכבים, makom
shene'ekar mimenu avodas kochavim, if you see a place where idolatry has
been uprooted from, אומר ברוך שעקר עכו"ם מארצנו, omar baruch she'akar akum
me'artzenu, blessed be God that has uprooted idolatry from our land, presumably
specifically about
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. וכשם שנעקרה ממקום זה כן תעקר מכל מקומות
של ישראל, Ukeshem shene'ekrah mimmakom zeh ken te'aker mikkol mekomos shel Yisrael,
so it should be uprooted from all places where the Jewish people
are, והשב לב עובדיהם לעבודתך vehashev lev ovdeihem la'avodasecha and return the
hearts of their worshippers of idols to Your service. Now, ובחוץ לארץ,
ubachutz la'aretz, so that's in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ובחוץ לארץ אין
צריך לומר והשב לב עובדיהם לעבודתך. ubachutz la'aretz ein tzarich lomar vehashev
lev ovdeihem la'avodasecha. So although presumably you do say blessed are You
God that uprooted the land, maybe you wouldn't say מארצנו me'artzenu that
uprooted the idolatry, you would not say return the worshippers to Your
service. Why? מפני שרובו עובדי כוכבים mipnei sherobo ovdei kochavim because that's
idolaters, we're not concerned that they would return to God, which is
a little bit against the whole universalist message that we just got
through saying in the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right, which is ובכן תן פחדך
על כל המעשים. u'vchen ten pachdecha al kol hama'asim. So the next
response is, which the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק, paskens, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר אף בחוץ לארץ צריך לומר כן, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
af bachutz la'aretz tzarich lomar ken, no, even in חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz you say it, מפני שעתידים להתגייר, mipnei she'atidim lehisgayer, because we
look forward to the time when even the idolaters will ultimately convert.
Now you didn't have to say convert, you could have just said
will ultimately acknowledge God. Anyway, it's framed— להתגייר. lehisgayer. Exactly, להתגייר. lehisgayer.
I know, but here it frames it as convert, שנאמר אז אהפוך
אל עמים שפה ברורה, shene'emar az efpoch el amim safa berura, then
I will turn to all the nations one clear language,
I think it's לקרוא כולם בשם ה', likro kulam beshem Hashem, I
believe is the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Now again, it doesn't
have to be framed as convert, but that's at least the way
the גמרא Gemara can frame it here. Yes.
I think that's exactly what it means because when you acknowledge God,
really acknowledge God, you've converted. You haven't formally gone through some process
but you're saying השם Hashem is like the one God.
Yes, but there could be—the גמרא Gemara understands that there—the proper sort
of, you know, universal economy or whatever categorization understands that there—the
non-Jews
should acknowledge God as the only one true God, observe the שבע
מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach and they don't have to
actually become Jewish. You don't call that להתגייר. lehisgayer. That's a true
acknowledgement of God. Well, we're just talking about idolaters. Okay, so you're
saying להתגייר lehisgayer means to convert from idolatry to worship of God,
not to convert to Judaism.
Right, we're just talking about idols.
Right, okay, right. So it could be. Now I do want to
say—one minute—I do want to say something else. So that's one thing.
And a, whether we look forward to, you know, the non-Jews abandoning
idolatry. Would you say נעקר? ne'ekar? Presumably according to both of them
you say uproot idolatry from the land even if it's not the
land of Israel, that's seen as a good thing. Now the question
is about this ברכה. bracha. which is recognizing that, you know, this
ברכה bracha to say that God, he has patience to those who
transgress, do we continue to say that nowadays when we see, you
know, עבודה זרה? avoda zara? Now partly this was an issue for,
you know, for us, it could be a question, let's say, you
know, I don't know, you're going to, you know, India and you're
seeing all these Hindu temples and so on. But, you know, the
ראשונים rishonim who also very much, you know, there's all this history
question about how Christianity has been treated as עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
not as עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it evolved, you know, an evolution
of an attitude whether it's, you know, differences between how it's seen
for Jews, how it's seen for non-Jews. But anyway, תוספות tosfot raises
the question: why don't we make this ברכה bracha when we see,
basically, churches? Why don't we say שנתן ארך אפיים לעוברי רצונו? shenatan
erech apayim l'ovrei ritzono?
And תוספות tosfot says: maybe because, you know, you would only do
it on a new phenomenon. If the stuff is always around, like
the same way you only make a ברכה, bracha, let's say, when
you see the Mediterranean if you haven't seen it in the last
thirty days, so if the stuff is always around you, you don't
make a ברכה. bracha. And maybe the only time you make this
ברכה bracha is when a new church or a new idol is
being erected. And he suggests that's why it gives the example of
מרקוליס, markolis, because מרקוליס markolis you're constantly erecting new little statue or
new little, you know, things of symbols, you know, these statues or
whatever, these pyramids. So תוספות tosfot says maybe that's why you only
make it when it's a new phenomenon and maybe that's why we
don't make it nowadays. Yes, Charlie, you want to say something?
Like what if you have a situation the other direction where you
say have for instance a church that's been converted to a mosque
or even a synagogue?
Oh, that's interesting. Would you say...? Again, that's a real question nowadays,
you know, given the evolved, even within the period of תוספות, tosfot,
how the attitude towards Christianity evolved, there'd be a question about whether
they would think to make that ברכה. bracha. Here at least תוספות
tosfot does not, gives a different reason why the ברכה bracha isn't
made. But, you know, yeah.
But מרקוליס markolis is very positive. What? It's positive, this blessing of
מרקוליס. markolis.
It's positive in the sense that,
well, it recognizes that there's an aspect of idolatry, of an idolatrous
worldview, which does not, does not include a type of violence,
non, unethical...
Oh, that's an interesting point.
So there is an ethical, there is positive, it does have an
ethical foundation to an ultimately idolatrous...
Oh, that's a very nice point. So it's a sublime...
In the Jewish worldview.
I hear you, that's a beautiful point. I hadn't thought of that
in regard, I thought of it as just an articulation of: how
do we deal with reality that there's idols all over the place,
especially in the time of the גמרא, gemara, in this pagan world?
How do we explain how God tolerates that? So we give an
expression to that in a ברכה. bracha. What you're saying is the
expression actually says that God can tolerate this phenomenon. So what does
that say also about our attitude towards these types of things, which
is an excellent point. Yeah.
But, you know, so the idol can still be around as long
as the worshippers are no longer there, right? I mean, let's say
I go to Rome and you
know, you see a bunch of like... That's not clear. It does
sound like it's very much related to the, to the, what do
you call it? To the artifacts of the עבודה זרה avoda zara
and not to the worshippers of the עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. So this is my question, that there are words for
that, like צלמים tzalamim or פסילים. psilim.
Now עבודה זרה avoda zara actually, we have come to think, to
use the word, because of all the way in which the גמרא
gemara have been self-censored to say עכו"ם, akum, we've used the word
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you know, to עכו"ם akum to mean non-Jews
or non-Jewish worshippers, but in the גמרא gemara it most classically means
actually the idols, the objects. Okay.
So the people this would be worshipping, in other words...
Yeah, the people are around but the exact artifacts are not.
And they mean this even if they're worshipping like the sun and
the moon, right? In other words, you can't break the sun or
the moon.
Yeah, exactly, right.
Okay, so yes, let's keep on, let's go over. The גמרא gemara
says like this, okay. דדרש המונא, Dadrash Hamuna, הרואה בבבל הרשיעה, Haroeh
b'Bavel harishia, now
we're going from, from idolatry to wicked nation, the wicked Babylon, which
is interesting because you know at least the אמוראים amoraim had a
pretty good in בבל. Bavel. But בבל Bavel is still the רשיעה
rishia because it destroyed, you know, they were the ones that destroyed
the second בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So צריך לברך חמש ברכות. tzarich
l'varech chamesh brachot. You have to give five blessings. Now again, this
is fascinating because coming up with new ברכות, brachot, you know, we've
seen this already that we're not in the משנה. mishna. ראה בבל
אומר Ra'a Bavel omer when you just see בבל Bavel you
say ברוך שהחריב בבל הרשיעה. Baruch shehechariv Bavel harishia. So בבל Bavel
is now basically associated with Iraq, right? So maybe particularly after the
Iraq war we could make this ברכה. bracha. Anyway,
ראה ביתו של נבוכדנצר Ra'a beito shel Nevuchadnetzar apparently as long as
you walk enter into the country, again, one wonders you know, I
mean they were living there.
Was he from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or was he from בבל?
Bavel?
I don't remember, I think he was בבל Bavel but I could
be wrong. Anyway, ראה ביתו של נבוכדנצר Ra'a beito shel Nevuchadnetzar what
you say a ruin in בבל? Bavel? Maybe.
I was going to say something about that.
Well, let's keep on going. It doesn't say that, but let's keep
on saying. ראה ביתו של נבוכדנצר אומר, Ra'a beito shel Nevuchadnetzar omer,
if you see the house, the palace of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar that's destroyed,
you say ברוך שהחריב ביתו של נבוכדנצר הרשע. Baruch shehechariv beito shel
Nevuchadnetzar harasha. Okay, that God destroyed the house of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar הרשע.
harasha. ראה גוב של אריות או כבשן האש, Ra'a gov shel arayot
o kivshan ha'esh, if you see the, you know, the pit of
the lions or the fiery furnace... ראה גוב של אריות או כבשן
האש, Ra'a gov shel arayot o kivshan ha'esh, if you see the,
you know, the pit of the lions that Daniel was thrown into
or the fiery furnace that Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah were thrown into,
then אומר omer ברוך שעשה נסים לאבותינו במקום הזה. Baruch she'asa nissim
la'avoteinu bamakom hazeh. At least that's the ברכה beracha in the משנה.
Mishnah. You did miracles for our forefathers.
רבה בר כובי, Rabba bar Kobi, which,
the V-Y, the V-Y one, you somehow knew which one it was.
Yep.
Okay, so now רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, which was I guess a
common one, a common sight in בבל, Bavel, אומר omer ברוך שנתן
ארך אפים לעוברי רצונו, Baruch shenatan erech apayim le'ovrei retzono, blessed is
the one who gives patience, you know, extending the anger against those
who transgress. ראה מקום שנוטלין ממנו עפר, Ra'a makom shenotlin mimenu afar,
you see a place they take dust from it, or where presumably
well we'll see what it means, אומר omer ברוך אומר ועושה גוזר
ומקיים. Baruch omer ve'oseh gozer umekayem. Blessed is the one who does
and fulfills, makes an edict
and fulfills it. What does this mean? רש"י Rashi has two explanations.
One is that there was some curse that no animal could leave
בבל Bavel unless it was laden down with the dust from בבל
Bavel and another was that, you know, you couldn't grow anything there
and you only used the land for a place of taking dust
to build things from. But somehow there was some aspect in which
there was a space turned to dirt and that was seen as
a curse of בבל Bavel and that was a source of using
dirt and transporting it to other places. Yes.
According to Koren, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was the second generation אמורא
Amora in בבל. Bavel. Right. And what I also know is that
by that time, the city of בבל Bavel itself was actually in
ruins. Ah. So it had been completely abandoned.
What is the city of בבל? Bavel? I thought בבל Bavel was
a country.
Well, the Babylon was a city.
Oh, Babylon was also a, aha.
That was the capital city of Babylonia.
Yeah. I see. What does it correspond to nowadays, do we know?
It's just a ruin.
It's been, it's been, so it's sort of like חרבה בבל בחורבנה.
charva Bavel bechurbanah.
Yes, so an entire
city, it doesn't mean the entire country of בבל. Bavel.
Okay, that makes more sense. So the practical שאלה sheila is if
an American soldier in Iraq actually went to the ruins, would he
have to say this ברכה?
beracha? Right. There, which museum is it? Is it the British Museum?
British Museum where you can see what is it, the temple of,
yeah,
British Museum, they took most of the artifacts and took them to,
yeah.
Okay.
Now was that also where the Tower of Babel was? בבל? Bavel?
Yeah.
Yeah. But there's also מדרש midrash about that but we're not getting
into it now. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רבא כי הוה חזי חמרי דשקלי עפרא, Rava ki hava chazi chamrei
deshakelei afra, when רבא Rava saw donkeys that were taking dirt from
בבל, Bavel, טרף להו ידא אגבייהו, taraf lehu yada agabayihu, he basically
patted, you know, smacked them on the back, patted his hands on
their back, ואמר רהטו צדיקי רהטו, ve'amar rehatu tzaddiki rehatu, run righteous
ones, run, these are the donkeys, למעבד רעותא דמרייכו, lema'avad re'uta demarayichu,
to do the will of your master, somehow taking dirt from בבל,
Bavel, there's some apparently understanding that it would be turned to dirt
and that it would be used as a source of, you know,
excavating dirt. Okay. מר בריה דרבינא כי הוה מטי לבבל, Mar berei
deRavina ki hava mati leVavel, when he was coming to בבל, Bavel,
again now thanks to Charlie's explanation or Steinsaltz's explanation, meaning the ruined
cities of Babylon, of בבל, Bavel, הוי שקיל עפרא בסודריה, havi shakil
afra besudrei,
he would take dust from in his
handkerchief, ושדי לברא, veshadei levara, cast it outside of the city, לקיים
מה שנאמר וטאטאתיה במטאטא השמד, lekayem ma shene'emar vetatetiha bematateh hashmad, I
will sweep it out with the broom of destruction, so you know
sweeping out the dust of בבל. Bavel. אמר רב אשי אנא הא
דרב המנונא לא שמיע
לי, Amar Rav Ashi ana ha deRav Hamnuna lo shemia li, I
didn't hear the ruling of רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna about these five
blessings, אלא מדעתי ברכינהו לכולהו, ela mada'ati berachinhu lechulehu,
I on my own thought I should make ברכות berachos and it
happened to be the exact same five that he said. It's quite
fascinating. That, yeah, it was just a century later. Right, they're composing
their own ברכות, berachos, just happened to be the exact same ברכות.
berachos. Okay.
Three times? He means like what, once every 30 days? If they
lived in בבל?
Bavel? Presumably, I don't know, something like that. But maybe Charlie's right,
it's a ruin city, how often do you visit a ruin city?
Okay. דף נ"ח עמוד א'. Daf nun chet amud aleph. אמר רבי
ירמיה בן אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu ben Elazar, נתקללה בבל, nitkalela Bavel,
so now we're talking about בבל Bavel being destroyed, a little digression
here. If בבל, Bavel, when בבל Bavel was cursed, נתקללו שכניה, nitkalelu
shecheneha, all its neighbors were cursed as well, like אוי לרשע אוי
לשכנו. oy lerasha oy lishcheno. נתקללה שומרון, Nitkalela Shomron, when שומרון Shomron
however was cursed, נתברכו שכניה, nitbarechu shecheneha, its neighbors were blessed. How
do you see this? נתקללה בבל נתקללו שכניה דכתיב, Nitkalela Bavel nitkalelu
shecheneha dechtiv, ושמתיה למורש קיפוד, vesamtiha lemorash kipod, I will make it
for an inheritance of the קיפוד, kipod, which is some type of
a bird, but it basically might mean a wasteland, nobody can use
it, ואגמי מים, ve'agmei mayim, and, you know, ponds of water, so
it'll be useless, everybody around and also, you know, will be hurt
by this destruction.
נתקללה שומרון, Nitkalela Shomron, I mean if it's a wasteland, so that
affects the neighbors as well. But when שומרון Shomron was destroyed, נתברכו
שכניה. nitbarechu shecheneha. You see the Jews are so good that even
when they're destroyed they leave over a blessing for their neighbors. דכתיב,
Dechtiv, as it says, ושמתי שומרון לעיי השדה למטעי כרם. vesamti Shomron
le'ei hasadeh lematayei karem. I will make שומרון Shomron into a heap
in the field into a planting of vineyards. So it'll be destroyed,
but at least you'll be able to plant vineyards in its place.
ואמר רב המנונא. Ve'amar Rav Hamnuna. Okay, back to ברכות. berachos. הרואה
אוכלוסי ישראל. Haroeh uchlosei Yisrael. Again, what you really see is fascinating,
right, the אמוראים Amoraim are, I mean look, I mean they can
do it, but you know the idea that they just, I guess
what surprises me is there doesn't seem to be any exact rules
here, right? It's just various things they think it's appropriate to make
ברכות berachos for they make. They composed various ברכות. berachos. So somebody
who sees הרואה אוכלוסי ישראל, haroeh uchlosei Yisrael, if you see a
masses of Israel, we'll see what the masses and number is in
a minute, אומר ברוך חכם הרזים. omer baruch chacham harazim. You make
a ברכה, beracha, blessed are You God, who is wise to secrets.
Also fitting in right with the themes of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, אתה יודע רזי עולם. atah yodeia razei
olam. ואוכלוסי עובדי כוכבים, v'uchlosei ovdei kochavim, if you see masses of
non-Jews, אומר, omer, בושה אמכם, boshah imchem, your mother is shamed for
presumably having given birth to all of you. So maybe specifically assuming,
let's at least hope that it's assuming in the context of, right,
and let's assume I also it's in the context about the fact
that they're idolaters and not just non-Jews. But yes, that is a
פסוק, pasuk, that's not a ברכה. beracha. And then that why it
raises questions in the ראשונים Rishonim as I said, whether all these
ברכות berachos are with שם ומלכות, shem u'malchus, are they formal ברכות,
berachos, or are they without שם ומלכות? shem u'malchus? And because we
often see, you know, here, like if you see the mirror image
of it wasn't a ברכה beracha but just a פסוק. pasuk. So
there are some ראשונים Rishonim that think for all of this, it's
without שם ומלכות, shem u'malchus, including ברכות berachos like that we make
on, you know, thunder and lightning and the ones that we do
make with שם ומלכות. shem u'malchus. There are ראשונים Rishonim that say
basically all the ברכות berachos in the ninth פרק perek are without
שם ומלכות. shem u'malchus. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, הרואה אוכלוסי ישראל, haroeh
uchlosei Yisrael, if you see the, you know, masses of Israel, אומר
ברוך חכם הרזים, omer baruch chacham harazim, wise to one's secrets. What
does that mean? שאין דעתם דומה זה לזה, she'ein da'atam domeh zeh
l'zeh, because their, you know, that what one person is thinking is
not what the other one is thinking. ואין פרצופיהם דומים זה לזה,
v'ein partzufeihem domim zeh l'zeh, and what one the one person looks
is not like how the other person looks. So when you see
so many, and now I think this is really quite a beautiful
ברכה beracha because you could say when you see three people, two
people, everybody is unique. But when you see a mass of people,
you tend to forget about the individuals and you just and you're
overwhelmed by, oh my God, there's a million people here and it
can be actually completely effacing about the, you know, about the individual
uniqueness. So it's exactly at that time where you emphasize that, you
know, we might sort of, you know, sort of see all these
people and think about them in like big abstract numbers. But actually
each one of them is unique and distinct and created with the
divine image and God is able to sort of see the uniqueness
of every individual. So there's something very beautiful about this which is
not just about the greatness of God, but about a reminder of
us not to lose the face of the individual even in, you
know, particularly these times, particularly, you know, when there's so many people
you're especially if you're, you know, you're having a big event, you
know, how many people showed up? Oh my God, there was 500
people came to the event and you completely, you know, it's very
easy especially when you see so many people to forget about, you
know, each person who's there as an individual.
Okay, yeah, and a non-universalist
thread here that, I mean you could make the same ברכה beracha
on non-Jews, right?
Right. So that is, right. So then again the question, is this
about non-Jews, is it specifically about idolaters? But yes, right.
I mean certainly, you know, I don't think we're saying that we
see them as all like, you know, the same.
Yeah, but right. I mean it's true, I mean God obviously they're
unique as well and individual as well. But it is true that,
you know, who was it, you know, I think David Berger once,
Dr. David Berger wrote an article about universalism and Jewish attitudes towards
non-Jews. He said, you know, when it comes to Jews, we know
there are צדיקים, tzaddikim, there are רשעים, reshaim, there are בינוניים, beinonim,
there are people that are, you know, you know, they're people
that have different professions, they're people that have different things. Non-Jews, the
other 99.99% of the world, we think they're all the same, they're
just non-Jews. So
it's sort of like this, they're the non-Jews, they're not part of
our interest. So you're right, there's there is definitely some of that.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, בן זומא
ראה אוכלוסא על גבי מעלה בהר הבית. Ben Zoma ra'ah uchlosa al
gabi ma'alah b'Har HaBayis. Ben Zoma saw a huge mass of people
when he was standing on a step of הר הבית. Har HaBayis.
Now if you might remember yesterday, what did it say about בן
זומא? Ben Zoma? Do you remember what it said yesterday? It said
by בן זומא Ben Zoma he was one of the sages that
if you see him יצפה לחכמה. yitzapeh l'chochmah. So here's what ברכה
beracha he made.
He said, אמר ברוך חכם הרזים, amar baruch chacham harazim, blessed is
God who is wise to the secrets of every individual, וברוך שברא
כל אלו לשמשני, u'baruch shebara kol eilu l'shameshni, and
that He created all of these people just to serve me. So
let's see what that means. הוא היה אומר, hu hayah omer, he
used to say, כמה יגיעות יגע אדם הראשון עד שמצא פת לאכול.
kamah yegi'os yaga Adam HaRishon ad shematza pas le'echol. How much effort
did אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon have to go into to make bread?
חרש וזרע וקצר ועמר ודש וזרה ובורר וטחן והרקיד ולש ואפה, charash
v'zara v'katzar v'amar v'dash v'zara v'borer v'tachan v'hirkid v'lash v'afah,
he had to seed and harvest and heap up into a
heap, thresh and winnow
and select from the chaff from the grain,
grind and sift, knead and bake, ואחר כך אכל, v'achar kach achal,
he was one person here all the steps he had to do.
ואני, v'ani, but I, משכים ומוצא כל אלו מתוקנים לפני. mashkim u'motzei
kol eilu metukanim l'fanai. All of these are right in front of
me, you know, I have people maybe bring the wares to my
door, I go to the supermarket, you know, if you think about
how many different people and how many different... Steps were involved in
producing this. So on the one hand, it's a beautiful point. It's
like, don't take this stuff for granted, to appreciate how much,
how many people were involved in the creation of this and have
a little הכרת הטוב hakarat hatov for all of those people. But
there is a little bit of the sense of that well let's
finish but the sense of it's all to serve me is a
little interesting. Let's keep on going. We'll get back to that. וכמה
יגע אדם הראשון עד שמצא בגד ללבוש. v'khama yaga Adam HaRishon ad
shematza beged lilbosh. How much effort did he go to until he
had clothing to wear? גזז, gazaz, he had to shear the sheep,
ולבן, v'liben, and whiten the wool, ונפץ, v'nipetz, combed it, וטוה, v'tava,
וארג, v'arag, and spin it and weave it, ואחר כך מצא בגד
ללבוש. v'achar kach matza beged lilbosh.
Only then did he have clothing. ואני משכים ומוצא כל אלו מתוקנים
לפניי. v'ani mashkim u'motzei kol eilu metukkanim lefanai. I get up and
I go to the store and all this is already done for
me. Okay, so כל אומות שוקדות ובאות לפתח ביתי kol umot shokdot
u'baot lepetach beiti or אומניות ummaniyot is probably the better גרסא. girsa.
All these different craftspeople are coming to my door to sell me
their wares. ואני משכים ומוצא כל אלו לפניי v'ani mashkim u'motzei kol
eilu lefanai and I find all this prepared for me.
Okay, so if you stop here, it's very beautiful, it's הכרת הטוב
hakarat hatov for all the people that were involved in the production.
However, if you and we'll see the next story also really emphasizes
the הכרת הטוב, hakarat hatov, but juxtapose this to the לשמשני, leshamesheni,
they're there for me, basically means like I'm the pinnacle of creation.
It doesn't say like how we're all interdependent and everybody has to
be grateful for everybody's contribution and so on. And I would say
for example that Rambam in מורה נבוכים, Moreh Nevuchim, who also was
a bit of an intellectual elitist, also talks along this vein, like
that the whole purpose of creation is for the few theologians that
will real or philosophers that devote all of their time to really
understanding truth and understanding God and that everybody else in the world
exists because if you didn't have everybody else in the world,
these theologians, these philosophers wouldn't have clothes and wouldn't have homes and
wouldn't have food. So you need everybody else in order to produce
the few people for whom the world really exists. Very platonic. What?
Very platonic idea. So there definitely is, and here Ben Zoma was
this חכם, chacham, could have been a very similar type of an
approach. Let everybody else do all of these sort of crafts and
material tasks, I'll focus on my intellectual pursuits.
But so there is maybe an echo or more than an echo
of that, but there also hopefully is a profound element of הכרת
הטוב hakarat hatov and we will see that in the next story.
So let's take a look.
How about all of these people that have this ברכה beracha of
חכם הרזים, Chacham HaRazim, which is definitely a ברכה beracha that we
see, don't have the rest of it?
No, this is just something he made for himself.
And what about these אוכלוסיא uchlosya as הכרת הטוב? hakarat hatov?
We'll get to that. We haven't said that yet. Let's keep on
going.
Did Ben Zoma have a profession?
I don't know, it's a good question. Before it mentioned that he
was a חכם. chacham. He was definitely also wealthy, it says everybody
was bringing this stuff to his house. Okay, let's take a look.
Now we really move on to the theme of הכרת הטוב. hakarat
hatov. Okay, he says like
this: הוא היה אומר, hu haya omer, he used to say, אורח
טוב מהו אומר, oreach tov mahu omer, what does a good guest
say? כמה טרחות טרח בעל הבית בשבילי. kama trachot tarach ba'al habayit
bishvili. How much effort did the homeowner do for my sake? Here
I was, I came to his home, look at all the effort
he put forth for me. כמה בשר הביא לפניי, kama basar hevi
lefanai, he made this nice meal with all of this meat that
he made for me. כמה יין הביא לפניי, kama yayin hevi lefanai,
he brought this wine for me. כמה גלוסקאות הביא לפניי, kama gluskaot
hevi lefanai, pastries. וכל מה שטרח לא טרח אלא בשבילי. v'kol mah
shetarach lo tarach ella bishvili. He did all of this just for
me, I have to be so grateful. So notice again the בשבילי,
bishvili, but the בשבילי bishvili is not about I'm fabulous, but בשבילי
bishvili is I have to perceive it that this was done for
my sake so I have the profound gratitude for everything that was
done. And that might really inform the previous בשבילי. bishvili. אבל אורח
רע מהו אומר, aval oreach ra mahu omer, what does a bad
guest say? מה טורח טרח בעל הבית, mah torech tarach ba'al habayit,
what type of effort did he go to? He didn't really put
himself out. פת אחת אכלתי, pat achat achalti, he only gave me
one loaf of bread. חתיכה אחת אכלתי, chaticha achat achalti, he gave
me a little slice of meat. כוס אחד שתיתי, kos echad shatiti,
he gave me a little glass of wine. כל טורח שטרח בעל
הבית לא טרח אלא בשביל אשתו ובניו. kol torech shetarach ba'al habayit
lo tarach ella bishvil ishto u'vanav. He just did it for the
rest of his household, he just threw on another plate, he'll have
me come along, but he didn't really put himself out for me
at all. So here it's very significant that you're supposed to see
it as that it was done for you, not to see that
you're the center of the world, but that you
have that debt of appreciation, that sense of deep appreciation for what
was done. Don't dismiss it, like you could say, look, all these
people that are making clothes and food or whatever, they're doing it
for their living, they're not doing it for me, why should I
feel grateful for them? They're doing it to make a living, they're
doing it to make a פרנסה. parnasa. So he says no, you
should look at it as they are, whatever their motivation is, they
are doing this, they have now given this to you, you are
the beneficiary of all of their efforts, so you have to perceive
it as if it were done for you in order that you
have that depth of gratitude. So it really has a lot to
do with your perception and an issue of הכרת הטוב. hakarat hatov.
So I think it's much better to read his statements that way
than to read it as like I'm the pinnacle of creation. All
right, אורח טוב מה אומר? Oreach tov mah omer? What does it
say about a good guest? זכור כי תשגיא פעלו אשר שוררו אנשים.
Zachor ki tasgi poalo asher shoraru anashim. Remember that his actions are
great and that people have sung for regarding him, so that you
should see the greatness of the actions of the בעל הבית Ba'al
habayit and sing his praises. אורח רע Al oreach ra see, by
a bad guest what does it say? לכן יראו אנשים, Lachen yeu
anashim, therefore people will see, I forget the end of the פסוק,
pasuk, but it's something bad. Okay, so I think they quoted it
bad. Anyway, ויהי בימי שאול זקן בא באנשים. Vayehi bimei shaul zaken
ba ba'anashim. So now we're, now we're going back to the theme
about אוכלוסא. uchlosa. The person in the time of שאול Shaul was
old, coming with men, which is interesting. What does it mean coming
with men? אמר רבא ואיתימא רב זביד ואיתימא רב אושעיא, Amar Rava
ve'isayma Rav Zvid ve'isayma Rav Oshia, this is ישי אבי דוד, Yishai
avi Dovid, Dovid's father, שיצא באוכלוסא ונכנס באוכלוסא. sheyatza be'uchlosa venichnas be'uchlosa.
Wherever he would go, whenever he would leave his home, whenever he
would come out, it would be with a huge retinue of people
to show the honor associated. So that's obviously tying into the אוכלוסא
אוכלוסא uchlosa uchlosa theme. כי דרש באוכלוסא, Kedarsh be'uchlosa, whenever he would
give a דרשה, drasha, you know, a lecture, it would be with
a huge mass of people. אמר עולא נקטינן אין אוכלוסא בבבל. Amar
Ulla naktinan ein uchlosa be'Bavel. We take the position now for אין
אוכלוסא בבבל. ein uchlosa be'Bavel. We don't see, you know, this idea
of אוכלוסא uchlosa does not apply in בבל, Bavel, which is interesting.
Presumably even if you have a large number of people, you know,
somehow this sort of status of it representing כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
now we're going to get to a shift. Until now it's been
about the uniqueness of the individuals and so on. Now we're getting
to, I think, it, I guess, representing כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. So
it doesn't have significance in בבל. Bavel. Even if you have a
lot of people, it wouldn't be considered אוכלוסא. uchlosa. Right, exactly. תנא,
Tanna, and now we get to a number. אין אוכלוסא פחות מששים
ריבוא. Ein uchlosa pachot mi-shishim ribo.
אוכלוסא Uchlosa 600,000, which obviously is equivalent to those that left ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, left מצרים. Mitzrayim. So it sounds now that there's
a shift, that אוכלוסא uchlosa represents like a כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
So therefore you need 600,000 and maybe only in Israel. Different than
what the emphasis I thought seemed to be before. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabanan. So that's the אוכלוסא. uchlosa. Now we move on to another
ברכה. bracha. Yeah, if you were here, if
you were there and you got
600,000 people together, you wouldn't... well, Jews maybe, I don't know. How
many did they have at the סיום הש"ס? Siyum HaShas? 100,000. 90,000.
All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. הרואה חכמי ישראל אומר ברוך שחלק
מחכמתו ליראיו. Haroeh chachmei Yisrael omer Baruch shecholak mechachmato lireiaiv. A new
ברכה, bracha, but this is Tanna'itic. If you see wise people of
Israel you make the ברכה bracha that You have given from Your
wisdom to those who fear You. חכמי עובדי כוכבים אומר ברוך שנתן
מחכמתו לבריותיו. Chachmei ovdei kochavim omer Baruch shenatan mechachmato livriyotav. Wise non-Jews
or even idolaters you say ברוך שנתן מחכמתו לבריותיו. Baruch shenatan mechachmato
livriyotav. It's important because, you know, as opposed to before we were
somewhat dismissive and wouldn't make any ברכה bracha or whatever, you can
say negative things, here we actually acknowledge the wisdom of the non-Jews.
Just don't call them יראי אף, yirei af, especially if it means
idolaters. Okay, but they're God's creatures and we see that this is
from God's wisdom, wisdom as a divine gift. Okay. הרואה מלכי ישראל
אומר ברוך שחלק מכבודו ליראיו. Haroeh malchei Yisrael omer Baruch shecholak mikvodo
lireiaiv. If you see Jewish kings you say blessed is He who
gives from His glory, His honor, to those who fear Him. That
the honor of the kingship is a sort of is some, you
know, some shadow, some echo of the divine honor. מלכי עובדי כוכבים
אומר ברוך שנתן מכבודו לבריותיו. Malchei ovdei kochavim omer Baruch shenatan mikvodo
livriyotav. Same idea, you don't have ליראיו, lireiaiv, but you have לבריותיו,
livriyotav, but still the same basic ברכה. bracha. One of the differences
is I noticed you have חלק cholak by the Jews but נתן...
natan...
Oh, that's an interesting point as well. חלק Cholak might mean like
it's more of a חלק, chelek, it's
more a little bit of the essence of the thing. Okay, that's
a good point. Some have the גירסא girsa here instead of לבריותיו,
livriyotav, לבשר ודם, lebasar vadam, to flesh. It's like the difference between
giving light, where
you don't diminish your own, so כבוד, kavod, you know, if you
have כבוד kavod for a king, that can diminish your כבוד kavod
for God, whereas wisdom... No, but they're both... No, his point is
that when it's the Jews, it's חלק chilek and
when
it's the non-Jews, it's נתן. natan. When you say חלק, chelek, you're
sort of like almost including, no?
חלק, Chilek, חלק, chilek, right, חלק, chilek, חלק. chilek.
Thank you. It's not חלק. cholak. חלק, Chilek, thank you. But it
gave of a portion has Michael is right, has more of a
sense of it's somewhat closer to the essence or something. Yes.
Why stop there with those attributes of God? What if you see
like Mother Teresa?
Right, his חסד chesed or whatever. Yeah, it's a good point. It
is a good point. You know, maybe those things are not as,
you know, maybe people don't tend to be as distinguished. I mean,
it is true you might have the Mother Teresas, but I'm sure
you could put a lot more people on the list of who
you would put in the genius list than who you would put
on the amazing חסד chesed list. People tend to be more distinguished.
א מלך A melech is clearly identified and the חכמה chochma is
also, you know, maybe more clearly distinguished, but it is a great
question. Why specifically those two? I will tell you that there's an
important halachic literature
about, about do you make a ברכה bracha when you see contemporary
rulers of nations, like rulers of nations, presidents, or even kings of
democratic nations and so on. The general מסקנא maskana is that you
don't because they don't have, number one, the same absolute power that
kings have, and number two, they don't have the same type of
glory that kings have, you know? You don't have the horses riding
in front of them and the trumpets. I mean, there is obviously
some of it, but it's not the same degree. Like even in
England, who has the glory but not really any power. Right, and
sometimes you have one without the other. So they basically say you
make the ברכה bracha without שם ומלכות. shem u'malchut. Oh, like Queen
Elizabeth, she has- have, exactly. I was basically saying that in those
days you make the ברכה bracha without שם ומלכות, shem u'malchut, which
I had the occasion to do once when I, well, about- about
eight years ago, something like that, anyway, Dvor was invited to the
president's חנוכה Chanukah party and I came as her guest. So anyway,
so all right, anyway, אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, לעולם ישתדל
אדם לרוץ לקראת מלכי ישראל ולא לקראת מלכי ישראל- l'olam yishtadel adam
larutz likrat malchei Yisrael v'lo likrat malchei Yisrael לרוץ לקראת מלכי ישראל-
larutz likrat malchei Yisrael a person should always run to greet Jewish
kings, ולא לקראת מלכי ישראל בלבד, v'lo likrat malchei Yisrael bilvad, not
only Jewish kings, אלא אפילו לקראת מלכי עובדי כוכבים, ela afilu likrat
malchei ovdei kochavim, even non-Jewish idolatrous kings, שאם יזכה יבחין בין מלכי
ישראל למלכי עובדי כוכבים. she'im yizkeh yavchin bein malchei Yisrael l'malchei ovdei
kochavim. If you merit, and רש"י Rashi here says he doesn't say
it in other places, live at the time of משיח Mashiach and
you see what the honor of the king of- king משיח Mashiach
is, then you'll be able to appreciate how radically different that is
than the current honor that is afforded to non-Jewish kings. Yeah. רב
ששת סגי נהור הוה. Rav Sheshet sagi nahor hava. רב ששת Rav
Sheshet was blind. הוה קאזיל וכולי עלמא לקבולי אפי מלכא. hava ka'azil
v'chulei alma l'kabulei apei malka. Everybody was going to greet the king.
וקאזיל בהדייהו. v'ka'azil bahadeihu. He went with them. Now that's quite interesting
because he lived in בבל Bavel while I guess they had- yeah,
they had שבור מלכא Shapur Malka was- yeah, they did have a
king. Okay, anyway, okay, anyway, everybody was going to greet the king
and he was going with them. וקאזיל
בהדייהו. v'ka'azil bahadeihu. רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, he went with them. אשכחיה
ההוא צדוקי, Ashkechei hahu tzaduki, a certain Sadducee- what did they have
there? מין. min. המינא? ha'mina? Yeah, I figured. Okay, anyway, a certain
heretic found him. אמר להו, Amar lehu, חצבי לנהרא, Chatzvi l'nahara, you
know, you take- you take whole vessels to a river to draw
the water. כגני למה? Kagnei lamah? So who needs broken vessels at
a river, right? What are you going to do with them? So
you're blind, why are you going? אמר ליה, Amar lei, תא חזי,
ta chazi, come see. Interesting "come see." Okay, תא דידענא טפי מינך.
ta d'yadana tafi minach. I know more than you. חלף גונדא קמייתא.
Chalaf gunda kamaita. So the first retinue of, you know, passed. כי
קא אוושה, Ki ka avsha, when they were making all this noise,
you know, they were shouting out, playing the trumpets, whatever it was,
אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי amar lei hahu tzaduki or ההוא מינא, hahu
mina, אתא מלכא, ata malka, look, the king is coming! אמר ליה
Amar lei רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, לא קאתי, lo kati, he's not
coming yet. חלף גונדא תניינא. Chalaf gunda tinyana. The second retinue or
whatever group came, crowd passed. כי קא אוושה, Ki ka avsha, when
they were making all this noise, אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי amar lei
hahu tzaduki or ההוא מינא, hahu mina, השתא קאתי מלכא. hashta kati
malka. Ah, now he's coming. אמר ליה Amar lei רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, לא קאתי lo kati מלכא, malka, he's not coming yet. חלף
תליתא. Chalaf tlita. The third group came. כי קא שתיקא, Ki ka
shatka, now it was silence. So אמר ליה amar lei רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, ודאי השתא אתי מלכא. vadai hashta ati malka. Now the
king is coming. Everyone said, "shhh," enough. Okay, anyway, he was the
only one talking. Anyway, no, now the king is coming. אמר ליה
Amar lei ההוא צדוקי hahu tzaduki or ההוא מינא, hahu mina, מנא
לך הא? mena lach ha? How do you know? How do you
know now? אמר ליה, Amar lei, דמלכותא דארעא כעין
מלכותא דרקיעא. d'malchuta d'ara k'ein malchuta d'rakia. The- the- the kingship below
is some essence, some echo of the kingship above. Also, you know,
the idea of the ברכה, bracha, שנתן מכבודו לבשר ודם. shenatan mikvodo
l'basar vadam. So it's somewhat similar to the kingship above. דכתיב, D'chtiv,
and what do we know about when God comes and, you know,
and appears? צא ועמדת, Tze v'amadata, so the famous פסוק pasuk by
אליהו, Eliyahu, צא ועמדת בהר לפני ה'. tze v'amadata bahar lifnei Hashem.
Go- go to stand by the mountain. והנה ה' עובר ורוח גדולה
וחזק מפרק הרים ומשבר סלעים, v'hineh Hashem over v'ruach gedolah v'chazak mefarek
harim u'meshaber sela'im, powerful wind breaking mountains and rocks, לפני ה' לא
ברוח ה'. lifnei Hashem lo baruach Hashem. God is not in the
wind. ואחר הרוח רעש, v'achar haruach ra'ash, and then there'll be tremendous
noise, לא ברעש ה'. lo bara'ash Hashem. God's not in the noise.
ואחר הרעש אש, v'achar hara'ash esh, and fire, לא באש ה', lo
ba'esh Hashem, not in the fire. ואחר האש קול דממה דקה, v'achar
ha'esh kol demamah dakah, after the fire, a still soft voice. So
after all of the big, you know, sounds and fanfare, then there's
quiet and that's when the king appears. Silence, right. The sound of
silence, exactly. כי אתא מלכא, Ki ata malka, so the king came,
פתח רב ששת וקא מברך ליה. patach Rav Sheshet v'ka mevarech lei.
He made the ברכה, bracha, אשר נתן מכבודו לבשר ודם.
asher natan
mikvodo l'basar vadam.
So אמר ליה amar lei ההוא צדוקי hahu tzaduki or ההוא
מינא, hahu mina, למאן
דלא חזיתיה קא מברכת? l'man d'la chaziteih ka mevarechet? You're making a
ברכה bracha to someone you didn't see? But apparently רב ששת Rav
Sheshet felt, you know, he- he was able to sense the כבוד
kavod that was given to him without actually having to- to see
it. It didn't require actually seeing it. So ומי, v'mai, but there's
a fascinating question in general, you know, about the ברכות brachot that
a blind person makes. Does the blind person make בורא, borei, you
know, the ברכה bracha in the morning, בורא מאורי האש, borei meorei
ha'esh, or no- the ברכה bracha I was talking about is the
morning ברכה bracha about- no, no, no, יוצר המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot is
a question in the גמרא. Gemara. Right, or let's say, right, let's
say the ברכה bracha when you see when you פוקח עורים, pokeach
ivrim, when you see a- trees blossoming. Let's say he goes out
and he smells the new trees blossoming, should he make the same
ברכה? bracha? Right, so it raises those important questions
in הלכה. halacha. Right, exactly. That- there's more technical issues with
that. Anyway, so
now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ומאי הוי ליה דהוא צדוקי דמינא *Umai hava
lei d'huhu tzaduki demina*, what was the end result of this min
because we have to assume we don't we need some closure, he
was mocking the whole way. So איכא דאמרי *Ikka d'amri*, some says,
חברוה כחלינהו לעיניה *Chavruah kachlinu le'einei*, his friends or whatever literally like
put mascara in his eye but it's a euphemism for poked out
his eye. Okay, obviously there's a מידה כנגד מידה *Midda k'neged midda*
here because he was mocking רב Rav ששת *Rav Sheshet* as being
blind, so somehow he got blind as the end. ואיכא דאמרי *Ve'ikka
d'amri*, and some say רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, this is very nice
and ironic, נתן עיניו בו ועשהו גל של עצמות *Nasa einav bo
ve'nasa gal shel atzamot*. That's the classic, that's a classic phrase in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that when a sage gives somebody the evil
eye and they turn into a pile of bones. But of course
it's a little ironic that רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* who couldn't see
was still able to give him the evil eye. So רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet* could see better when he was blind than other people
could see when they were with their eyes open. Alright. רב שילא
נגדיה לההוא גברא *Rav Shila nagdei lehu gavra*, I think we had
this before but anyway רב שילא *Rav Shila* gave lashes to a
certain person דבעא מצרית *De'ba Mitzrit* that had sex with a non-Jewish
woman with a מצרית *Mitzrit*. Is it a מצרית *Mitzrit*?
מצרית *Mitzrit*, א גויה *A goyah*.
Oh, I assumed so, thank you. Same like the צדוקי *Tzaduki*, another
perfect example of self-censorship. Right, thank you very much. Okay, non-Jewish woman,
thank you. אזל אכל בי קורצי בי מלכא *Azal achal bei kurtzei
bei malka*, so this person went and basically this is a phrase
אזל אכל בי קורצי *Azal achal bei kurtzei* which basically meant like
slandered in the house of the king. אמר Amar *Amar* he said,
איכא חד גברא ביהודאי *Ikka chad gavra biyehudaei*, there's a certain person
amongst the Jews דקא דיין דינא בלא הרמנא דמלכא *De'kadin dina belo
harmana demalka* that is making taking out acts of authority without the
king's permission he gave me lashes.
He was a well I don't know if he's a vigilante, he's
a בית דין *Bet din*,
it's one person.
Well, we don't know the whole story, man. We don't know that.
I mean maybe that's not clear. I mean you know there's clear
examples of you know Jewish self-government throughout the middle ages so I
wouldn't have interpreted this as a vigilante necessarily. Anyway so but he
was complaining to the king and he said he did it without
permission from the king, you know corporal punishment. שדר ליה פריסתקא *Shadar
lei pristacha*, so the king sent some troops to go collect collect
him. This is again going to be like a similar type of
מידה כנגד מידה *Midda k'neged midda* story with eye poking out as
before, you'll see how it's analogous. Anyway כי אתא *Ki ata*, so
when רב שילא *Rav Shila* was brought before the king, אמרי ליה
amrei lei *Amrei lei* they said to him, מאי טעמא נגדיתיה להאי
*Mai ta'ama nagdeitei lehacha*, why did you give lashes to this person?
אמר להו Amar lehu, *Amar lehu* he said to them, you know
the king's I don't know officers or whatever, דבעא חמרא *De'ba chamarta*,
he had sex with a donkey. So אמרי ליה amrei lei *Amrei
lei*, so they said to him, אית לך סהדי *Itlach sahadai*, do
you have witnesses? אמר Amar... להו *Amar lehu*, אין *In*, yes. אתא
אליהו Eliyahu *Ata Eliyahu*, so אליהו *Eliyahu* came to the rescue. אידמי
ליה כאינש *Itmei lei ke'inish*, he looked like a person and he
gave testimony that this man had sex with a donkey.
אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, אליהו *Eliyahu* as a person. Right, what does
this אליהו *Eliyahu* made himself look
like a person, maybe maybe that he didn't, maybe but yes sometimes
people know it's אליהו *Eliyahu*, so somehow he made himself look like
a non-angelic like a regular person. Okay, אמרי ליה *Amrei lei* they
said to him, אי הכי *Ihachi*, if that's the case, בר קטלא
הוא *Bar ktala hu*, he deserves to be put to death.
אמר להו *Amar lehu*, bestiality. He said to them no, I didn't
want to do that. אנן מיומא דגלינן מארעא *Anan miyoma de'galinan me'ar'a*,
from the day from the day we've been exiled from our land,
לית לן רשותא למקטל *Leit lan reshu lemikta*, we don't have the
permission to execute people. So obviously it's saying you know here he
was being charged with taking too much authority into his own hands
and he's saying no no no actually first of all what I
did was totally justified and second of all God forbid that I
would take authority into my hands, corporal punishment you know that's inappropriate,
we don't do the death penalty these days, capital punishment, right. Yeah
yes yes okay a little okay. So anyway אתון מה דבעיתו עבידו
ביה *Atun ma de'ba'eitu avidu bei*, you do what you want. מוסר
*Moser* don't be well yeah. עד דמעייני ביה דדינא *Ad d'me'ayanei bei
dedina*, until while they were looking into this guy's judgment to decide
what to do with him,
the person who he had given lashes to, פתח רב שילא ואמר
*Pasach Rav Shila ve'amar*, רב שילא *Rav Shila* opened up a פסוק
pasuk *Pasuk* and said,
yes yes no מלקו
*Malko*, לך ה' הגדולה והגבורה *Lecha Hashem hagedulah vehagevurah*, to you God
is the greatness. So presumably again to say like ultimately he gives
his allegiance to God and not to these you know temporal kings
a king. אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, so they said to him, מאי
קאמרת *Mai ka'amrat*, oh what are you saying? So in that funny
language, אמר להו *Amar lehu*, הכי קאמינא *Hachi ka'amina*, this is what
I am saying. בריך רחמנא *Baruch rachmana*, praise is God, דיהב מלכותא
malchuta בארעא כעין מלכותא malchuta דרקיעא *De'yahav malchuta be'ar'a ke'ein malchuta derakia*,
that he has given to the kingship on the land similar to
the kingship in heaven. Obviously echoing the נתן מכבודו לבשר ודם *Natan
mikhvodo lebasar vadam* and the story of the previous story the kingship
of the land, but here the point being that he was really
giving glory to God but when challenged about it he said that
he was acknowledging... meaning that, you know, the kingship below is representative
or comes from the kingship above.
So again giving recognition to the king. ויהב להו שלטנא and he
has given to you just, you know,
judgment or dominion ורחמי דינא ve-rachmei dina and your people that love
justice and therefore I am giving thanks to God that you are,
you know, his emissaries here on earth. אמרו Amru they said חביבא
לך יקרא דמלכותא Chaviva lach yekara de-malchuta oh my God I never
realized you were so appreciative of the honor of the kingship and
you're so respectful of the king's authority. יהבו ליה קולפא Yehavu leh
kulpa so they gave him a rod which demonstrated his ability to
be a judge. They made him into a judge. So obviously you
know the irony here is shot through. Okay, anyway,
אמרו ליה Amru leh they said to him דון דינא Dun dina
go ahead now you can be a judge as well for us.
כי הוה נפיק Ki hava nafik as he was going out of
the king's palace אמר ליה ההוא גברא Amar leh ha-hu gavra so
this person who's now being taken in and might be seeing the
death penalty pretty soon, he said עבד רחמנא ניסא לשקרי Avad Rachmana
nisa le-shakrei God did miracles for liars? Look what he did. He
turned it all around for you and you lied. הכי אמר ליה
Hachi amar leh so he God did such? אמר ליה Amar leh
he said to him רשיעא Rashia wicked לאו חמרי קרינהו Lav chamarei
karinhu what are you talking about? They're called donkeys. דכתיב אשר בשר
חמורים בשרם De-ketiv asher besar chamorim besaram the flesh of donkeys is
their flesh. Right, very disparaging to say the least, common the Gemara
quotes sometimes relating to non-Jews and now we certainly understand why the
censorship of the text from גוי Goy to מצרי. Mitzri. So
חזייה דקאזיל למימרא להו דקרינהו חמרי Chazyei de-ka'azil le-meimra le-hu de-karinhu chamarei
so now he saw this guy was going to turn around and
undermine everything he had accomplished and tell the king he just called
you guys donkeys. אמר so he said האי רודף הוא Hai rodef
hu this guy is now a רודף rodef he's threatening my life.
והתורה אמרה הבא להורגך השכם להורגו Ve-ha-Torah amrah ha-ba le-horgecha hashkem le-horgo
if somebody's coming to kill you you have to beat him to
the punch, which you might say he already did by getting him
under the death penalty. Anyway מחייה בקולפא Machyei be-kulpa he smacked him
with the rod that he was given, the rod to be a
judge וקטליה ve-katleih and he killed him. So similar to the whole
Rav Sheshet story, besides the idea of the מלכותא below and the
מלכותא above, the blind person who made fun of Rav Sheshet became
blind and here's this person who tried to get Rav Shela in
trouble,
in the end was killed. Okay obviously raises some disturbing questions which
now we're going to hear.
Go for it. We miss you Rachel. Go for it.
I just don't understand the point. Is this rabbi as powerful?
The point is don't mess with the rabbis.
There you go.
You really think that's the point?
Yes, but
that's the Talmud's theme.
Yes, rabbis have power. They can either with their eyes turn you
into a pile of bones or because אליהו will come to their
aid and things will turn out in their to their betterment. So
A: don't mock them and B: don't oppose them, you know, and
submit to their authority.
I think clearly that's the point here. Right.
Then I mean I meant to understand that this that there was
an underhanded way of getting this point across and he wins at
the end because he has the authority to do it.
And he has right behind him and God will make everything work
out. I definitely think that's the point: don't mess with the rabbis.
I
might just make one little linguistic comment here.
This phrase חביבא עליה יקרא דמלכותא. Chaviva alei yekara de-malchuta. Yes.
So that
does seem to
echo הכרת הטוב.
Hakarat ha-tov.
So הכרת הטוב. Hakarat ha-tov.
Yes. Which I've found very difficult to actually find that
expression, the phrase. Yes. I think it's spelled with a ק Kof
not with a כ. Kaf. It's not the recognition of טוב tov
but it's dearness or its value.
I'm not sure. We'll have to check that. The phrase כפוי טובה
Kafui tovah is very common.
כפוי טובה Kafui tovah is somebody
who's ungrateful and I think the opposite of that would be not
to reject it but to acknowledge it. Anyway, I'm not sure. I'd
love to we could we could investigate. Oh, good. That's all I
wanted to say. Okay, yeah. Alright, let's go on here. So now
the Gemara says like this:
אמר... Where were we? חביב עלי הדין קרא דאיתעביד לי ביה ניסא,
chaviv alay hadain kra deitavid liy beih nisa, since this פסוק pasuk.
a miracle was done to me, לך השם הגדולה והגבורה lecha Hashem
hagedulah vehagevurah etc, so דרשינא
ליה, darshina leh, let me make a nice דרש drash on the
פסוק. pasuk לך השם הגדולה, lecha Hashem hagedulah,
to You God is the greatness, זו מעשה בראשית, zu ma'aseh bereshit,
that's the creation of the world. וכן הוא אומר עושה גדלות עד
אין חקר, vechen hu omer oseh gedolot ad ein cheker, does great
things without, without, you know, cannot be understood, referring to מעשה בראשית.
ma'aseh bereshit. והגבורה מאי, vehagevurah mai, זו יציאת מצרים, zu yetziat mitzrayim,
שנאמר וירא ישראל את היד הגדולה אשר עשה השם במצרים. shenemar vayar
yisrael et hayad hagedulah asher asah Hashem bemitzrayim.
So we want to say גבורה gevurah there? To say גבורה, gevurah,
וירא ישראל את היד הגדולה אשר עשה השם במצרים ויאמינו בהשם ובמשה.
vayar yisrael et hayad hagedulah asher asah Hashem bemitzrayim vayaminu beHashem uvmoshe.
No,
I don't know, anyway, not exactly sure how we get גבורה gevurah
there. Okay. Anyway, okay. Anyway, והתפארת, vehatiferet, glory, זו חמה ולבנה, zu
chamah ulevanah, the sun and the moon, שעמדו לו ליהושע, she'amdu lo
liyhoshua, that stood for Yehoshua.
There's a chronological order here. שנאמר וידום השמש וירח עמד shenemar vayidom
hashemesh veyareach amad
and the sun stood and the moon stood. I don't know if
it has the word תפארת tiferet there, but somehow it's, I don't
know, they quote the whole פסוק pasuk there in Steinsaltz. But anyway,
somehow I don't think the word
תפארת tiferet is mentioned. Yeah, I don't think the exact word is
matching. I think we're just connecting it, yeah, to different conceptually. והנצח,
vehanetzach, right, also like a whatever, sorry, like a triumph, victory, thank
you, זו
מפלתה של רומי. zu mapaltah shel romi. Ah,
when God was, you know, Rome fell. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu
omer, really jumping fast forward in history, ויז נצחם על בגדי, vayiz
nitzcham al begadai, and there like, you know, their, how does it
translate? Something like, you know, their blood, their lifeblood, right, splattered on
my garment. But here the play of the word of נצח netzach
and, and you know, right, נצח. netzach. Okay.
וההוד, vehahod, glory, זו מלחמת נחלי ארנון. zu milchemet nachlei arnon. So
going little back in history, the war in the wadi of Arnon,
שנאמר על כן יאמר בספר מלחמת השם את והב בסופה ואת הנחלים
ארנון. shenemar al ken yomer besefer milchemet Hashem et vahev besufah ve'et
hanachalim arnon. Again, I don't know how we get הוד hod out
of that. כי כל בשמים ובארץ, ki chol bashamayim uva'aretz, everything that's
in the heavens and the earth, זו מלחמת סיסרא, zu milchemet sisra,
the war against Sisra, שנאמר מן השמים נלחמו כוכבים ממסילותם. shenemar min
hashamayim nilchamu kochavim mimesilotam. So that they come out of, the stars
came out of their heaven to cause the, you know, to make
things to reverse on Sisra. לך
השם הממלכה, lecha Hashem hamamlachah, to You God is kingship, זו מלחמת
עמלק. zu milchemet amalek. וכן הוא אומר כי יד על כס יה.
vechen hu omer ki yad al kes yah. So רש"י Rashi says
here because כס kes is a כיסא kise and a throne of
kingship. So when God is victorious over עמלק, Amalek, that is ממלכה.
mamlachah. So now we're looking more towards Messianic times. והמתנשא, vehamitnase, and
lifting up, זו מלחמת גוג ומגוג, zu milchemet gog umagog, the war
of Armageddon. וכן הוא אומר הנני אליך גוג נשיא. vechen hu omer
hineni elecha gog nasi. So מתנשא mitnase and נשיא, nasi, the ruler,
ראש משך ותובל rosh meshech vetuval of the Meshech and Tuval, these
places of Babylonia.
לכל לראש, lechol lerosh, for all heads. So אמר רב חנא בר
רב אמר רב יוחנן, amar rav chana bar rav amar rav yochanan,
אפילו ריש גרגיתא, afilu resh gargita, even the guy in charge of
drawing water from the well, מן שמיא מנו ליה, min shamaya manu
leh, has his authority from heaven. So this is also playing into
the theme about kingship below is somehow derived from kingship above. Anybody
who has any authority below comes from the kingship of heaven. Now
this is used in the גמרא Gemara elsewhere, you know, for a,
in an exclusive way, or at least, you know, maybe this idea
because there's discussions for example in the גמרא Gemara about a גר
ger cannot be a king or, and then questions about other positions
of authority, and so in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael they didn't have
a problem with it, if I remember correctly in בבל bavel they
did, and the idea that every position of authority, even a small
one, is significant is certainly being indicated and echoed here. ובמתניתא תנא,
u'vmatnita tana, in the ברייתא braita we
taught, משמיה דרבי עקיבא לך השם הגדולה זו קריעת ים סוף והגבורה
זו מכת בכורות והתפארת זו מתן תורה והנצח זו ירושלים וההוד זו
בית המקדש, mishmei de'rabbi akiva lecha Hashem hagedulah zu kriyat yam suf
vehagevurah zu makat bechorot vehatiferet zu matan torah vehanetzach zu yerushalayim vehahod
zu beit hamikdash, more simple chronology without quoting פסוקים, psukim, leading up
to the building of the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. Okay. Turning the
page, נח עמוד א. nun chet amud alef. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
הרואה בתי ישראל בישובן, haroeh batei yisrael beyishuvan, if one sees houses
of Israel in their settled, אומר ברוך מציב גבול אלמנה, omer baruch
matziv gvul almana, blessed is God that erects the boundaries of the
widow. Now presumably that means in ארץ ישראל. eretz yisrael. If you
look at רש"י Rashi he says כגון בישוב בית שני, kegon beyishuv
bayit sheni, so it would be a question, you know, what about
nowadays? Now of course, you know, certainly the idea, like תוספות Tosafot
says in the other case, something that's a very constant phenomenon you
wouldn't make. I assume though, you know, when the עליות aliyot were
beginning, the first עליה, aliya, the second עליה aliya and so on,
when one saw these houses going up and ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael
turning from a place desolate of Jews to a place in which
Jewish community was being rebuilt, you would make this ברכה. bracha.
I go on vacation, you know, and I would say it. Yeah,
I don't know anybody
who makes this ברכה bracha
now when you see, yeah. Anyway, I understand, what in the, in
the like Zionist, you'd make this ברכה? bracha? What does it mean
מציב גבול אלמנה? matziv gvul almana? Well, I don't know, it is...
And then the פסוק pasuk what do you know in the שבעתא
דנחמתא Shivta DeNechemta what's the פסוק pasuk we say? אנוכי אנוכי הוא
מנחמכם. Anochi Anochi Hu Menachemchem.
I mean a lot of the thing is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and ירושלים Yerushalayim is the אלמנה almanah and she will be consoled
when it is rebuilt and so on. But the גבול אלמנה gevul
almanah is a little bit of a mixed metaphor, that's true. But
it means you're re-establishing the presence of Jews in the bereaved land
of Israel. So it's interesting that I didn't know that religious do
they say that every time you see a city or if new
cities are being built or being expanded or something like that? All
right. אומר, Omer, you really then also show your politics about making
it when you see the settlements.
So, אומר, Omer, ברוך מציב גבול אלמנה. Baruch Matziv Gevul Almanah. Okay,
בחורבנן, be-churbanan, if you see them destroyed, אומר, omer, ברוך דיין האמת.
Baruch Dayan HaEmet. And there we have a straight דיין האמת Dayan
HaEmet ברכה. bracha.
But do they do that today?
Well, I don't know how much is still destroyed. I mean, if
you like an excavation, you mean? Interesting. I don't know, hard to
say דיין האמת Dayan HaEmet in the contemporary realities about anyway, about,
anyway, but the point is we say, I don't know people that
really make this. Okay, בתי עובדי כוכבים בישובן. batei ovdei kochavim be-yishuban.
So, houses of again, is it non-Jews? Is it idolatry? It sounds
like because of the contrast to בתי ישראל batei Yisrael it does
not mean idolatry but it means non-Jews. In Israel. Maybe in Israel.
What's your גרסה girsa there? Does it say גויים, Goyim, עובדי כוכבים,
Ovdei Kochavim, what does it say? ואומות העולם. ve-umot ha-olam. So here
you go. And another, right, so this is another self-censorship, which is
very clear. It's not idolatry, it just means non-Jewish homes. אומר, Omer,
אל נקמות ה' אל נקמות הופיע. El nekamot Hashem El nekamot hofia.
Fascinating. That's very different to seeing. Did I skip a line? I'm
sorry. בית גאים יסח ה'. Beit ge'im yisach Hashem. The house of
the haughty God should, you know, should destroy, wipe away. Very different
from if you actually see idols, you say, oh, God holds back
His anger. But if you see their homes, you ask for their
destruction. I don't exactly get the contrast there because if you would
think anything you would ask for the destruction of the idols, not
of the homes. בחורבנן. be-churbanan.
Just completely different sources.
Well, yeah, that could be what. This is a תניא רבנן. tanya
rabanan. What was the other? The other was a, also a תניא
רבנן. tanya rabanan. They were both... I'd have to see if they,
maybe if the other was a תוספתא. Tosefta. I don't know if
this is a תוספתא. Tosefta. Could be. בתי, Batei, if you see
them, if you say בחורבנן, be-churbanan, if you see them destroyed, אומר,
omer, אל נקמות ה' אל נקמות הופיע. El nekamot Hashem El nekamot
hofia. God is a God of vengeance and they got their comeuppance.
So again, under what context? Every time you see a house of
a non-Jew, specifically in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? But again, the contrast
of this to the idolatry is mind-boggling. What does יסח yisach mean?
I don't know. I thought it meant to wipe away. How does
it translate it there?
Let's see. יסח ה'. yisach Hashem. Destroy. It says destroy.
Okay.
But
I'm just thinking if the houses of these people were destroyed, they
wouldn't have idols, so they wouldn't have a place to live.
Well, that's what, well, that's what my code was saying. But here,
you know, why, again, it is, it is shocking, I would say,
that while very, you know, tolerant almost of the presence of the
idol, that as though, so here just seeing the homes, it's a
pretty shocking contrast.
Maybe in some versions it does say actually about בתי עבודה זרה.
batei avodah zarah. בתי, Batei, not בתי. batei. Right.
Actual, right, actual,
you
know,
places of worship. Right, right. But that's not the original meaning and
it's certainly clear, I mean, first of all, by your, the גרסה
girsa אומות העולם, umot ha-olam, by the contrast to בתי ישראל. batei
Yisrael. But even if it means houses of idolatry, it's still amazing
the contrast to houses of idolatry as opposed to the actual idols.
The actual idols, the ברכה bracha was much more tolerant.
So anyway, something to definitely look into.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. רב חסדא... Rav Chisda... Okay. עולא
ורב חסדא הוו קאזלי באורחא. Ulla ve-Rav Chisda havu ka-azlei be-orcha. Ulla
and Rav Chisda were going on the way. כי מטו אפתחא דבי
רב חנא בר חנילאי, Ki matu a-pitcha de-vei Rav Chana bar Chanilai,
when they came to the house of רב חנא בר חנילאי, Rav
Chana bar Chanilai, which apparently was, had, we'll see, fallen from greatness.
נגד רב
חסדא ואתנח. Nagad Rav Chisda ve-itnach. Rav Chisda basically like, you know,
moaned and let out a sigh. אמר ליה עולא, Amar lei Ulla,
אמאי קא מתנחת? amai ka-mitnachat? Why are you, why are you letting
out such a deep sigh? Why are you קרעכצן? krepching? Right. ואמר
רב, Ve-amar Rav, doesn't רב say אנחה שוברת חצי גופו של אדם?
anacha shoveret chatzi gufo shel adam? Like, a, you know, a, letting
out such like a deep sigh, it breaks half of the body
of a person. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ואתה בן אדם האנח בשברון מתנים. ve-atah
ben adam ha'anach be-shivron motnayim. Now you, person, you know, sigh with
the breaking of the, of the loins, so the thighs, which is
half of your body, so it's, you know, why are you letting
out such a sigh? ורבי יוחנן אמר אף כל גופו של אדם,
Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar af kol gufo shel adam, it destroys your whole
body. שנאמר, Shene'emar, והיה כי יאמרו אליך על מה אתה נאנח? ve-hayah
ki yomru eilecha al mah atah ne'enach? Why are you moaning, why
are you sighing? ואמרת אל שמועה כי באה, ve-amarta el shmuah ki
ba'ah, because of the report that I have heard, ונמס כל לב,
ve-namas kol lev, every heart has been melted away, it destroys the
whole body. So why are you moaning? Which of course has to
remind me of the story, right, three, three. Three Jewish women sitting
on a bench, older women, and they're like, first one says אוי.
oy. And then the second one says אוי. oy. And then the
third one says אוי ויי איז מיר. oy vay is mir. So
the two look at the third they say, I thought we agreed
not to talk about the
children. All right, so anyway, ברכות. Berachot. Okay, so why are you
sighing? אמרה ליה היכי לא אסנח, amra lei heichi lo esnach, how
could I not sigh? ביתא דהוו בי ששין אפייתא ביממא, beisa dehavu
bei shishin afyata biyomama, the house that had in it 60 bakers
in the day, וששין אפייתא בליליא veshishin afyata belaylia and 60 bakers
at night, ואפיין לכל מאן דצריך veafyan lechol man detzarich and they
would bake for whoever needed, meaning it was such a wealthy house
and it was so good to the poor. דלא שקלו ידם מכיסא,
delo shaklu yadam minkiysa, his hand would never be out of his
pocket, רב
חנה, Rav Chana, דסבר דילמא אתיא עני בר טובין, desavar dilma asya
ani bar tovin, maybe a poor person who comes
from a good family will come, and he's very sensitive about his
image. דאדמטי ליה לכיסא de-admati lei lekiyasa when I'm searching in my
pocket to get out my wallet, קמיכסיף kamichsif he'll be embarrassed that
he's standing there and waiting for alms. So he always had his
hand in his pocket so that nobody would have to wait, shouldn't
be embarrassed. ותו, vetu, and also, הוו פתיחין ליה ארבע בבי לארבע
רוחתא דעלמא, havu psichin lei arba bavei learba ruchta de-alma, they were
right exactly אברהם אבינו's Avraham Avinu text, there were four doors open
to the four winds or directions of the earth. Somebody I'm not
sure that מדרש Midrash actually exists about אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu. Somebody
told me they were once looking for it and couldn't find it
anywhere. Anyway, but here it exists by רב חנה. Rav Chana. Anyway
רב חנה בר חנילאי Rav Chana bar Chanilai I should say, four
doors were open to the four directions. וכל דהוה עייל כפין, vechol
de-avei ayil kafin, anybody that would go in hungry, נפיק דשבע nafik
desava would go out satisfied. והוו שדו ליה חטי ושערי בשני בצורת
vehavu shadu lei chiti us-ari bishnei batzoret
and would cast out wheat and barley outside of the window during
the times of a famine, אבראי abarai outside, דכל מאן דכסיף למישקל
ביממא dechol man dechaseif milemishkal biyomama anybody that would be embarrassed to
come to for alms during the day אתיא ושקיל בליליא asya veshakil
belaylia could pick
it up at night and nobody would see them. So it was
such a wealthy house and such a house that gave so much
to the poor and to the needy. השתא נפול בתילא hashata naful
be-tila now it's fallen in, it's in a mound. ולא אסנח velo
esnach
should I not moan? אמרי ליה so he said הכי אמר רבי
יוחנן hachi amar Rabi Yochanan this is what רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan
said, מיום שחרב בית המקדש miyom shecharav Beit HaMikdash since the day
the Temple was destroyed נגזרה גזירה על בתיהן של צדיקים שיחרבו. nigzera
gezeira al bateihen shel tzaddikim sheyecharavu. There was a decree that the
houses of the righteous should be destroyed. And I added specifically the
righteous שנאמר shenemar באזני ה' צבאות אם לא בתים רבים לשמה יהיו,
be-oznei Hashem Tzevaot im lo batim rabim leshama yihyu, if not great
houses will be for destruction, desolation, גדולים וטובים gedolim vetovim great and
good, מאין יושב me-ein yoshev no one will dwell in it. Right,
that's why it's צדיקים's tzaddikim houses. ואמר רבי יוחנן ve-amar Rabi Yochanan
עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחזירן לישובן. atid HaKadosh Baruch Hu lehachziran leyishuvam.
But don't worry God will eventually return them to the way they
were שנאמר shenemar שיר המעלות לדוד הבוטחים בה' כהר ציון shir hama'alot
ledavid haboteichim baHashem ke-har tzion who trust in God like Mount Zion.
מהר ציון עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחזירו לישובו mehar tzion atid HaKadosh
Baruch Hu lehachziro leyishuvo the same way that Mount Zion will be
restored, אף בתיהן של צדיקים עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחזירן לישובן, af
bateihen shel tzaddikim atid HaKadosh Baruch Hu lehachziran leyishuvam, even the houses
of the righteous. חזייה דלא מייתבא דעתיה. chazya delo meyashva da'atei. So
he saw right,
so עולא Ulla saw that it wasn't helping. רב חסדא Rav Chisda
was still very deep in despair, distraught. So he said אמרי ליה
דיו לעבד שיהא כרבו. dayo le-eved she-yeihe k'rabo. Look, we should, the
slave should be no better than the master, as God's house is
destroyed, maybe it would even be somewhat inappropriate if we were so
things were so good for us with the house of God being
destroyed. So quite fascinating, the way in which it was consoled here
by putting it in the context of the destruction of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. ארעא דמלכותא דשמיא. ar'a demalchuta deshmaya. Oh that's interesting
too, oh that's a very nice point, picking up that theme about
the kingship above. The kingship above on the ground is evocative of
what is above in the cosmological. Thank you, that's very nice. Okay,
תנו רבנן tanu rabanan let's read one more ברכה bracha here. הרואה
קברי ישראל אומר haroeh kivrei yisrael omer if you see graves of
Jews you say ברוך אשר יצר אתכם בדין baruch asher yetzar etchem
bedin blessed the one that created you with justice וזן אתכם בדין
vezan etchem bedin and sustained you with justice in your life וכלכל
אתכם בדין vechilkel etchem bedin also provided for you ואסף אתכם בדין
ve-asaf etchem bedin he also gathered you in with justice. So the
same way we acknowledge the goodness of God or the justice of
God in creating and sustaining you during your life, so this is
also being recognizing the justice in the death and it's a same
type of a ברכה bracha on a type of a דיין אמת
Dayan Emet ברכה bracha but here in a larger context. ועתיד להקימכם
בדין veatid lehakimchem bedin ultimately he will also bring you to life
with in with justice. Right, revive you. מר בריה דרבינא מסיים בה
משמיה דרב נחמן. Mar brei de-Ravina mesayeim bah mishmei de-Rav Nachman. So
מר Mar the son of רבינא Ravina gave the following closing to
this ברכה. bracha.
ויודע מספר כולכם
veyodeia
mispar kulchem he
knows all of your numbers, so don't worry he hasn't forgotten you,
even if you know many many have been buried that we don't
even that we've forgotten them. והוא עתיד להחיותכם vehu atid lehachayotchem he
will once again give you life ולקיים אתכם ulekayem etchem and to
establish you ברוך מחיה המתים baruch mechayei hameitim blessed is the reviver
of the dead. Yeah, this has, because it's long, so it's long,
it also has a סיום, siyum, and this is a ברכה bracha
that we actually make. I was once in a cemetery and I
didn't have a סידור siddur and couldn't find this ברכה bracha whatever,
but I had, I have like ש״ס Shas on my iPhone phone,
so I looked up this דף daf so I could find the
נוסח nusach of the ברכה bracha because I forgot the נוסח nusach
of the ברכה. bracha. Alright, קברי עובדי כוכבים, Kivrei ovdei kochavim, let's
finish this, the graves of non-Jews, אומר, omer, בושה אמכם, Busha imchem,
the same פסוק we quoted before, also about non-Jews or maybe idolaters.
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, הרואה את
חבירו לאחר שלשים יום, haroeh et chaveiro leachar shloshim yom, if you
see a friend and haven't seen him for the last thirty days,
אומר, omer, ברוך שהחיינו וקיימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. Baruch shehecheyanu vekiyemanu vehigianu
lazman hazeh. You make a ברכה bracha שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. תוספות Tosafot says
if it's a good friend, somebody you're happy to see. לאחר שנים
עשר חודש, Leachar shneim asar chodesh, twelve months, אומר, omer, ברוך מחיה
המתים, Baruch Mechayeh Meitim, because who knows what happens to somebody in
twelve months. So there's real questions if you make this ברכה bracha
nowadays when we know about people, you can be in contact with
them by phone, by email, so how much joy is there having
not seen them, how much is there a concern about what their
fate is if you're in regular contact? So most people don't make
this ברכה. bracha. I would just share with you that רב יואל
בן נון Rav Yoel Bin-Nun has many people know of him, he
says he does not like the idea that we become such like
ליטווקס Litvaks or whatever, that we're so concerned about ברכה לבטלה bracha
levatala that we override the opportunities for religious expression that the גמרא
has given us. So I remember once when I bumped into him
after having not seen him for a while, he made this ברכה
bracha with שם ומלכות, shem umalchut, at least the שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. I
don't think it was the מחיה מתים, Mechayeh Meitim, but at least
the שהחיינו. shehecheyanu.
Alright, I'll just do one more line because I know we have
to end. אמר רב אין המת משתכח מן הלב אלא לאחר שנים
עשר חודש. Amar Rav ein hameit mishtakeach min halev ela achar shneim
asar chodesh. You forget a dead person after, not forget, but there's
some type of a closure, it's not in the forefront of your
memory after
twelve months. שנאמר, Shene'emar, נשכחתי כמת מלב הייתי ככלי אובד. Nishkachti kemeit
milev hayiti kechli oved. I've been forgotten like a dead person from
the heart, I was like a lost vessel. And רש״י Rashi says
people stop looking for their vessels because it's a גמרא in בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia about making announcements for lost objects after a year.
So presumably the same idea that you forget a person if you
haven't been in contact with them after a year, so there's a
sense like there's a מחיה מתים. Mechayeh Meitim. He really haven't, they
haven't been in your thoughts and now you see them so that
is the ברכה bracha of מחיה המתים. Mechayeh Meitim. Okay, we will,
I'm just going to read this one last story, it's a great
story to end with, I'm sorry, but we'll just read this one
last thing. רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע הוו קאזלי באורחא.
Rav Pappa veRav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua havu ka'azlei be'orcha. So רב
פפא Rav Pappa and רב הונא Rav Huna were going in the
way. פגעו ביה בר חנינא בריה דרב איקא. pagu beih bar Chanina
brei deRav Ika. They encountered בר חנינא Bar Chanina the son of
רב איקא. Rav Ika. אמרו ליה, Amru leih, they said to
him, בהדי דחזינא, Bahadi dechazina, while we saw you as we were
getting close to you and we saw you from afar, בריכנא עלך
תרתי, berichna alach tarti, we make two ברכות. brachot. This is a
nice closure to what we have been discussing
before. ברוך שחלק מחכמתו ליראיו, Baruch shechalak meichochmato lireiaiv, that God gives
His wisdom to those who fear Him because you're such a wise
person, and שהחיינו shehecheyanu because we haven't seen you in a long
time. אמר להו, he said to them, אנא נמי כיון דחזיתינכו, Ana
nami keivan dechazitincho, when I saw you, כשישים רבוא בני ישראל, keshishim
ribo bnei Yisrael, you were so important to me it was like
seeing 600,000 Jews, it was such an amazing experience. בריכנא עלייכו תלתא,
berichna alaichu tlata, I made three ברכות brachot for you. הנך תרתי,
Hanach tarti, שהחיינו shehecheyanu and נתן מחכמתו ליראיו, natan meichochmato lireiaiv, וברוך
חכם הרזים, uBaruch Chacham Harazim, and the ברכה bracha we said at
the beginning of the discussion today, God knows the secrets of every
person. אמרו ליה, Amru leih, they said to him, חכימת כולי האי,
chakimat kulei hai, you're so smart, you think that's a little too
ingenious for us. יהבי ביה עינייהו ושכיב, yahavi beih einaihu veshachiv,
so they gave him the evil eye. Which is, exactly. So I
don't know, you can figure out how that ties together all the
themes we have been talking about.